Guide to the Union Settlement Association records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Union Settlement Association Records,
1896-1995
Union Settlement Association (New York, N.Y.)
31 linear ft. (in 59 document boxes, 5 flat boxes, and 13 tube boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079915
History
During the late 1800s Manhattan's East Harlem experienced a dramatic increase in population and economic activity as transportation lines were extended into the area and new housing was constructed. Successive waves of Irish, German, Jewish and Italian immigrants moved into tenement buildings and formed a vital community, establishing small businesses, benevolent societies and fraternal organizations. But the dense concentration of population also gave rise to a host of urban problems: poor housing, inadequate health care, lack of educational opportunities, and crime.
A similar increase in the social problems attending urban growth led reformers and philanthropists in England to establish Toynbee Hall, the first settlement house, in 1884. Originally distinguished by the commitment of educated upper and middle-class volunteers to "settle" in working class communities in order to understand their problems first-hand, the settlement model was imported to the United States in 1886 when Neighborhood Guild was established on New York's lower east side. American settlement houses were in the vanguard of efforts to provide social services in their neighborhoods through such programs as kindergartens, day care, hot lunches, health clinics, visiting nurses, camps, playgrounds and arts education. In addition, the settlements joined Progressive-era reform movements for improved housing, public health, and sanitation.
In 1893 members of the Alumni Club of Union Theological Seminary decided to establish a settlement house, and chose the growing neighborhood of East Harlem as the site for their work. In May of 1895, Seminary alumni William McCord and William T. Holmes moved into a second floor tenement at 202 East 96th Street. Within a year the settlement moved to larger quarters at 237 East 104th Street, where it remains to this day. With McCord as its first headworker, Union Settlement established a kindergarten and penny provident bank, maintained a public playground, and hosted clubs for adults and children. McCord was succeeded in 1901 by Gaylord S. White, who oversaw an expansion of activities to include summer camps, housing and health investigations, a music school, and the hosting of a nursing center operated by Henry Street Settlement. With its growing programs the settlement was soon cramped for space; a new building was erected and opened in 1913.
During the 1920s and '30s East Harlem's demography began to change as African-Americans and Puerto Ricans moved into the neighborhood. A significant number of Italian families remained in the area as well. This predominantly working class community was hit hard by the depression, and Union Settlement responded by establishing such programs as aid for the unemployed, a cooperative grocery, and a nursery school. The settlement was led during this period by Helen Harris, who later served as Director of United Neighborhood Houses. Harris was succeeded in 1940 by Clyde Murray, who worked during his tenure for the integration of an increasingly diverse East Harlem community through leadership in such organizations as East Harlem Council for Community Planning (originally founded at Union Settlement in 1912 as South Harlem Neighborhood Association); by expanding settlement programs to include consumer education, senior citizen activities; and through the incorporation of the formerly independent Sunnyside Day Nursery into Union Settlement.
During the 1950s and '60s East Harlem was the site of extensive construction of low-income public housing projects. Under the leadership of William Kirk, Union Settlement developed new programs to serve the changing community, such as a credit union, College Readiness (later federally funded as Upward Bound), Head Start, and services based in public housing facilities such as the Union-Washington Community Center at George Washington Houses. Established programs were expanded as well, including senior services and music education, the latter run during this period by the dynamic Blake Hobbs. Once again the growth of settlement activities demanded additional space. As part of a complex including the Leggett Memorial Children's Center and Gaylord White House, a new Union Settlement building was completed in 1964. In addition to expanding programs and services, Union Settlement led efforts to involve East Harlem residents in planning of urban development in the area. The East Harlem Project, run jointly with James Weldon Johnson Community Centers Inc., fostered citizen participation in urban planning around such issues as housing and schools. The settlement also worked with community organizations like the Metro-North Association and Massive Economic Neighborhood Development to plan additional social services and housing development in East Harlem.
From the 1970s to the 1990s, Union Settlement has continued to develop innovative programs for East Harlem residents, such as Settlement Home Care, providing home attendants for over 400 homebound elderly; adult education focusing on English as a Second Language; and co-sponsorship of Project Linkage, a senior housing with social programs; mental health counseling; and services for the HIV+ population through the East Harlem HIV+ Care Network. Executive Director Eugene Sklar, who first joined the settlement staff during the 1950s, now oversees the work of a thriving settlement beginning its second century in East Harlem.
Scope and Content
The Union Settlement Association Records document a century of the settlement's activities, and provide a unique view of the first wave of the settlement movement in America. They document social conditions, demographic change, political activity, philanthropy and social work in East Harlem with a strong emphasis on the urban renewal period of the 1950s and '60s. The records include: annual reports, board minutes and committee files, headworker and executive director files, program reports, community organization files, and visual materials such as photographs, maps and architectural drawings.
The origins and early history of Union Settlement Association are documented by publicity brochures, annual reports, board minutes, and headworker correspondence, included in the "Administration" and "Board of Directors" series. These items are supplemented by photographs and scrapbooks in the "Audio-Visual Materials" series, and by several printed histories filed in "Administration."
The impact of public housing development on East Harlem is well documented by records in the "William Kirk Files" and "Administration" series. In addition to records of Union Settlement sponsored programs and activities such as the East Harlem Project and the Franklin Plaza housing co-op, there are extensive files on such community organizations as the East Harlem Schools Committee, Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Metro-North Association and Metro North East Harlem Housing Society. The "Board of Directors" series contains committee files, reports and correspondence that provide additional insight on the period and the development of settlement programs in response to community change.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series I: Administration
Series II: Bosard of Directors
Series III: Nora Bowen Files
Series IV: Fundraising
Series V: William Kirk Files
Series VI: Alber Mayer Files
Series VII: Programs and Services
Series VIII: Audio-Visual Materials
Series IX: Oversize Materials
Subjects
Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.).; United Neighborhood Houses of New York, Inc. (New York, N.Y.).; East Harlem (New York, N.Y.)--History.; New York (N.Y.)--History.; New York (N.Y.)--Social Conditions.; Community centers--New York (N.Y.).; Human services--New York (N.Y.).; Immigrants--New York (N.Y.).; Public housing--New York (N.Y.).; Social service--New York (N.Y.).; Social settlements--New York (N.Y.).; Social work--New York (N.Y.).; Welfare--New York (N.Y.).; Administrative records.; Agendas.; Announcements.; Annual reports.; Architectural drawings.; Blueprints.; Brochures.; Budgets.; Case files.; Contracts.; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter).; Interviews.; Lists.; Manuals.; Maps.; Memorandums.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Organizational charts.; Photographs.; Plans (drawings).; Posters.; Reports.; Rosters.; Scrapbooks.; Child welfare workers.; Social workers.; Women social workers.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 1-59. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Boxes 53-59 contain program records of a confidential nature and are closed to researchers, with the exception of Union Settlement Association staff, board members, or their approved agents, until 2050. All other records are open to research.
Acquisition
1994 M-1994 Records Union Settlement Ass'n Gift
Gift of Union Settlement Association, 1994.
- Series I: Administration
  - Anniversaries, 1920-70 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meetings, 1902, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benefits, ca. 1945-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials, 1896-1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials, 1920's-30's (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials, 1940's (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials, 1950's-90's (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Budgets and Financial Statements, 1914-15, 1939-44 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budgets and Financial Statements, 1945-48 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Budgets and Financial Statements, 1962-69 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buildings, 1940-64 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Christmas, 1942-69 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - City Planning Commission Report, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1902, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contributions, 1946-53 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Corporate Certificates, 1902-43 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Day Care Council of New York, 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - East Harlem Child Care Committee, 1961-64 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - East Harlem Churches, 1944-64 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - East Harlem Community College, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - East Harlem Community Corporation, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - East Harlem Community Organizations, 1955-70 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - East Harlem Merchants Association, 1954-56 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - East Harlem Merchants Association, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - East Harlem Merchants Association, 1958-66 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - East Harlem Merchants Association Small Business Survey, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fall Conference, 1947-63 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fall Conference, 1964-68 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Field Work Students, 1930-57 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Guest Lists, 1951-77 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Headworkers-Gaylord White, 1901-32 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Headworkers-Clyde Murray, 1947-49 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ellen S. Marvin "As I remember Union Settlement,", c.1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1911-95 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Interviews, 1994-95 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Summer Camp, [nd] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lee W. Walters "Union Settlement, Union Seminary: Settlement Work in the Gospel Tradition,", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Jun-Oct 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Nov-Dec 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Jan-Apr 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, May-Jun 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Jul-Oct 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, Nov-Dec 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Massive Economic Neighborhood Development, 1968-70 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memos, 1942-73 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Metro-North Association, 1962-63 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Metro-North Association, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Metro-North Association, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Metro-North Association, 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Metro-North Association, 1968-69 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Metro-North Association, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Metro-North Association: Citizens Committee, 1963-64 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Metro-North Association: Citizens Committee, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Metro-North Association: Citizens Committee, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Metro-North Association: Citizens Committee, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Metro-North Association: Citizens Committee, 1968-69 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Metro-North Association: Project Area Committee, 1969-71 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Metro-North Association: Schools Committee, 1966-70 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society, 1964-65 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Metro-North East Harlem HousingSociety, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society, 1968-69 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Chase Manhattan Bank, 1967-68 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Construction and Rehabilitation, 1962-64 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Construction and Rehabilitation, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Federal Housing Administration Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Gypsum Buildings, 1966-69 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Federal Housing Administration Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Roewack Building, 1967-69 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Federal Housing Administration Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Teper Buildings, 1966-69 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Edward Grey, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Gutterman Building, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Incorporation, 1965-66 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Metropolitan Hospital, 1966-68 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Minutes, 1965-69 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Overburdened Families, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: P.S. 50, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: P.S. 50, 1967-69 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Publicity, 1966-67 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Relocations, 1966-68 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Subcommittees, 1968-69 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Teper Buildings, 1965-66 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Teper Buildings, 1967-69 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Metro-North East Harlem Housing Society: Teper Buildings-Operations, 1965-68 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Metro-North Rehabilitation and Redevelopment Company, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital, 1966-69 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Museum of the City of New York, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Narcotics, 1951-57 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - National Conference On Day Care for Children, 1960-61 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Neighborhood Affairs Committee, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, 1895-1988 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Organization Charts, 1939-67 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Public Relations, 1940-48 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Publications: Annual Report, 1902 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Publications: Annual Report, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1923, 1932, 1934, 1938, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1945, 1948, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1961, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1966-68 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1969-71 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1972-74 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1975-79 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Publications: Annual Reports, 1980-95 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Publications: "News From Union Settlement,", 1966-76 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Newsletters, 1913, 1941-61 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Publications: "Union Settlement Reporter,", 1993-94 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Publications: "Union Settler,", 1941, 1946-48 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Puerto Rican Students Union, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Report-"New York City's Puerto Ricans", 1952 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Report-Self Study, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Residence, 1943-58 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Settlement Steering Committee, 1956-68 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Staff Lists, c.1932-77 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Staff Manuals, 1942-56 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Staff Meetings, 1948-63 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Staff Planning Committee, 1947-49 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Staff Publications-"The Girl and Her Chance," by Harriet McDoual Daniels, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Staff Schedules and Descriptions, 1951-54 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Staff Supervision, 1949-54 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Staff Training, 1941-43, nd (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Staff Weekend Conferences, 1953-57 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Statistics, 1947-58 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Teachers College, 1956-64 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Union Contracts, 1953-55 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Union Theological Seminary, 1914-31 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Washington Houses Community Center: "A Study of George Washington Houses,", 1955-56 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Washington Houses Community Center: Newsletter, 1957-64 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Washington Houses Community Center: Newsletter, 1965-70 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Washington Houses Community Center: Statistics, 1962-68 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Washington Houses Tenants Association, 1959-60 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Gaylord White House Community Center, 1964-69 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Winter Carnival, 1949-50 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series II: Bosard of Directors
  - Agendas, 1961-71 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Committees: Composition, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Committees: Executive, 1932, 1941, 1961, 1964-65 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Committees: Finance, 1940-41, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Committees: Lists, 1912-13, 1948-68 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Committees: Miscellaneous, 1929, 1941, 1950, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Committees: Scholarship Fund, 1940-47 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, l908-50, 1959-73, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "Functions of the Board of Directors,", [nd] (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Headworker's Reports, 1941-42, 1961-63 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - A, 1948-52, 1963-68 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Auchincloss, 1923, 1939-49, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - B, 1947-54, 1963-70 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Bennett, 1965-66 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Brown, 1930-52 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - D, 1951-54, 1960-67 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - G, 1950-68 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Goodhart, 1939-51 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - H, 1968-69 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Iselin, 1942-52 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Jacob, 1959, 1962-69 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - K, 1952-67 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - L, 1946-53, 1960-69 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - M, 1931-74 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Nicely, 1930-64 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - P-R, 1938-68 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Peck, 1932, 1939-51 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Ripley, 1947-67 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - S, 1963, 1968-69 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Schell, 1951-58 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Schell, 1959-68 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Sloan, 1930-52 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Swift, 1931-68 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Vance, 1952-70 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Van Dusen, 1945-70 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, (Bound Volume), 1898-1903 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1915 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1940-43, 1956-57, 1963-67 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Rosters, 1898-1970 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Constitution, ca. 1941, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, 1936-44 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1939-53 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Ellen Marvin, 1913-17 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1939-41 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1942-43 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1944-46, 1949, 1950, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Rosters, 1899-1964 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Series III: Nora Bowen Files
  - Adult Involvement Committee, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - All Day Neighborhood Schools, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Colby College, 1966-68 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Committee of 19, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Community Board 11, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Consumer Education, 1963-68 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Consumer Groups, 1966-68 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1964-71 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - De Witt Clinton Houses, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - East Harlem Council for Community Planning, 1961-67 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - East Harlem Project, 1957-59 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - East Harlem Project, 1960-61 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - East Harlem Project, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - East Harlem Project, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - East Harlem Project, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - East Harlem Project, 1965-67 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - East Harlem Project, 1968-71 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - East Harlem Project-Fundraising, 1961-63 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - East Harlem Project-Peace Corps, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - East Harlem Public Housing Association, 1963-64 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - East Harlem Schools Committee, 1956-60 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - East Harlem Schools Committee, 1961-62 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - East Harlem Schools Committee, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - East Harlem Schools Committee, 1964-65 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - East Harlem Schools Committee, 1966-68 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, 1959-66 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, January-June 1967 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, July-December 1967 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School Improvement Committee, 1970-71 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Liaison and Consultant Committee, 1961-63 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Neighborhood Organization Study Conference, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 105th Street Boy Scouts, 1968-71 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Schools-P.S. 108, 1958, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Schools-P.S. 168, 1958-64 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Schools-Screening Committee for School District 2, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Twenty-Third Precinct, 1964-70 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Wilson Houses, 1960-61 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Wilson Houses, 1962-64 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Youth Employment Service, 1961, 1966-67 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Youth Employment Service, 1968-71 (Box 20, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Fundraising
  - 40th Anniversary, 1935 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - 50th Anniversary, 1944-46 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Appeals-Foundations, 1942-48 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Appeals-General, 1915-48 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Appeals-Summer, 1914-49 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Contributions-Analysis, 1944-49 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Contributions-Correspondence, 1940-43 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Contributions-Correspondence, 1944-45 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Contributions-Correspondence, 1946-48 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Development Proposal, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Dinner Parties, 1947-48 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - "Drawing,", 1948-49 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Fashion Show, 1948 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Foundations (A), 1928-34, 1942-49 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Foundations (B), 1942-47 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Foundations (C), 1932-37, 1941-48 (Box 22, Folder 6)